<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two arguments in Parliament the first concerning the cannons, the second concerning the premunire vpon those cannons / by Edward Bagshawe, Esquire.</title>
            <author>Bagshaw, Edward, d. 1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69617</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B401</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16597</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12256038</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12256038</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57493</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69617)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57493)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 163:26 or 254:E164, no 12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two arguments in Parliament the first concerning the cannons, the second concerning the premunire vpon those cannons / by Edward Bagshawe, Esquire.</title>
                  <author>Bagshaw, Edward, d. 1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 43 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Miller,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library and Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ecclesiastical law --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Royal supremacy (Church of England)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57493:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57493:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO ARGUMENTS In PARLIAMENT, THE FIRST <hi>CONCERNING THE</hi> CANNONS, THE SECOND <hi>CONCERNING THE</hi> PREMVNIRE Vpon thoſe CANNONS.</p>
            <p>By <hi>EDWARD BAGSHAWE</hi> Eſquire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>George Miller,</hi> M.DC.XLI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:57493:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57493:2"/>
            <head>THE FIRST ARGVMENT <hi>CONCERNING</hi> THE CANNONS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. SPEAKER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE order this day is to debate the legality of the Cannons only and not the Premu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire, which divers have argued that the Clergy have encurred by making and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing theſe Cannons; but of that of the Praemunire I ſhall not now ſpeake, but when an order is made therof I ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare my opinion.</p>
            <p>I hold three illegallities, 1. In the Cannons, <hi>Primae Claſſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. In the Oath contained in the ſixt Cannon.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the Cannons, <hi>Secundae Claſſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. In that they are againſt Clergy and Laity without their common conſent.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That they were not well created by any of the Kings Writs or Commiſſions to inable them to make Cannons, which were not made in a Convocation, or in a new Synod derived out of an old
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:57493:3"/>Convocation, as was wittily obſerved by a noble Lord, but they were made in a meere convention of the Clergy, who had no war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant or authority to do as they did.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The matters contained in the ſaid Cannons are againſt the fundamentall Laws and Statutes of the Realme: In prooving all which, I will not inſiſt upon any thing that hath bin ſaid before, as fearing that I ſhall otherwiſe trouble you too long.</p>
            <p>The firſt point that I ſhall endeavour to proove, is, that the Clergy neither ſince nor before the Sta. of 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 19. could ever make Cannons and Conſtitutions that ſhould bind the Clergy and Laiety without their common conſent. For the prooving whereof I muſt make uſe of a Rule put in the 1. Booke of the Pandects of <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian, Tit. De origine iuris. Inconveniens eſt, omiſſis principijs &amp; origine non repetita illotis manibus materiam tractare,</hi> He doth not handle, but ſlubbers a queſtion, who deduceth it not from the fountain.</p>
            <p>And therefore I will caſt the whole Clergy, into five Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of time, from CHRIST to this very day, and in them all I ſhall proove this point, it being the maine thing and of the greateſt concernement to the liberty of the people.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is from CHRISTS time till the dayes of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> above three hundred years after CHRIST, in all which time there was no diſtinction, betwixt cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes civill and Eccleſiaſticall, but both were tryed before the temporall Judges of Emperours and Kings, as appeares plainly in the Imperiall conſtitutions, neither will any <hi>Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> deny it; for to ſpeake properly no cauſes that come in Judgement are ſpirituall or temporall in reſpect of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: For what reaſon can any man give me, why mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tryed at this day by the temporall Judge ſhould be leſſe ſpirituall then Adultery tryed by the ſpirituall Judge, when the truth is that Adultery is farre more carnall and ſenſuall then murther is; But the true reaſon of the difference is from the graunt of Emperours and Kings, who have given Conuſans of this to the Eccleſiaſticall
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:57493:3"/>Judge, and of the former to the Temporall.</p>
            <p>And the true Reaſon why Emperours and Kings in this firſt age had the Conuſans of all cauſes whatſoever, as belonging to their temporall Courts is; For that in thoſe times, there was no difference betwixt Biſhops and Prieſts in point of Juriſdiction, but they were all one, and had then no more to doe then to order the Churches by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent and godly preaching, adminiſtring the Sacraments, beating down Hereſies and Schiſmes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that this may not ſeeme ſtrange, becauſe I ſay it, though I could backe it with a multitude of Authorities, both old and new: Yet becauſe I am loath to ſpend time, I will onely cite two which are of good credit with the Clergy.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is out of the decrees of the Cannon Law compi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by <hi>Gratian, diſtinct.</hi> 95. <hi>cap. olim.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Rubricke. Presbiter idem est qui: Epiſcopus: ac ſola conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine praeſunt Epiſcopi Preſbiteris.</q>
            <q>
               <hi>TEXT,</hi> Olim idem erat Preſbiter qui &amp; Epiſcopus &amp; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tequam Diaboli inſtinctu ſtudia vel ſchiſmata in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gione fierent &amp; diſceretur in populis ego ſum Pauli: ego ſum Apollo: ego autem Cephae: communi Preſbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terorum concilio Eccleſiae gubernabantur, poſtquam au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem decretum eſt in toto orbe, ut unus de Preſbiteris ſupponerctur, ut ſchiſmatum ſemina tollerentur. Sicut ergo Preſbiteri ſciunt ſe ex Eccleſiae conſuetudins eſſe ſubiectos: Ita Epiſcopi noverint ſe magis conſuetudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne quam dispenſationis Dominicae veritate Preſbite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris eſſe maiores &amp; in communi debere Eccleſiam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere.</q>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond is out of Biſhop <hi>Jewell</hi> in the defence of his Apology, approoved by both Houſes of Parliament, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be in Churches, 2 <hi>Par. ca.</hi> 3. <hi>Diviſ.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>In S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Jeroms</hi> time (ſaith he) there were <hi>Metropolitans, Arch-biſhops, Arch-deacons and others,</hi> but CHRIST appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not theſe diſtinctions of orders from the beginning;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt. a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l Tit c.</hi> 3.</note> theſe names are not found in all the Scriptures, This is the thing that we defend, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Jerome</hi> ſaith, Let Biſhops underſtand
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57493:4"/>that they are in authority over Prieſts more by cuſtome then by order of GODS Truth; Theſe be S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Ieromes</hi> words truly tranſlated. And <hi>Part.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. <hi>Diviſ.</hi> 1, 2. he hath theſe words.</p>
            <p>I grant there be many ſpeciall priviledges granted upon great and juſt conſiderations of the meere favour of the Prince: That a Prieſt being found negligent or otherwiſe offending in his Miniſtry ſhould be convented and puniſhed, not by the Temporall or Civill Magiſtrate, but by the diſcretion of the Biſhop, yet you muſt remember (M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Harding</hi>) that all theſe and other like priviledges paſſed unto the Clergy from the Prince, and not from GOD, and proceeded only of ſpeciall favour and not of right; for from the beginning you know it was not ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond Stage or Tract of time, is, from <hi>Conſtantines</hi> dayes untill the Conqueſt, in which time the Emperours of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Kings here in England gave to Biſhops divers Juriſdictions and Priviledges over the Prieſts, which they had not before, as you may ſee in the Code and Novels of <hi>Iuſtinian.</hi> They had likewiſe Conuſans graunted to them of all cauſes concerning Matrimony and Teſtaments, which I could tell you by what meanes they firſt obtained theſe two, were it directly pertinent to this Point. But the Power and Right of making Eccleſiaſticall Lawes were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver reſerved to Emperours and Kings with the aſſent of the people, and not to the Biſhops and Clergy.</p>
            <p>To omit the Imperiall Conſtitutions of <hi>Conſtantine, Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Put out by <hi>Lambert.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Iuſtinian,</hi> and other Emperours, it appeares plainly in our <hi>Saxon</hi> Lawes made long before the Conqueſt, by theſe ſeverall Kings, <hi>Ina, Alfred, Edgar, Canutus, Edward</hi> the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor,</hi> &amp;c. that all Eccleſiaſticall Lawes, both concerning Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Diſcipline were made by them, <hi>Cum conſenſu Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermannorum &amp; populi,</hi> in their <hi>Michel: Gimot,</hi> or great Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, which is all one with our Parliament. Nay, to their very Councels and Synods, the Laiety did come if any mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was there handled which concerned them. Of this I could give likewiſe many inſtances, I will only name one, the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell or Synod at <hi>Winchester</hi> called in the 5<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. yeare of King <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutus,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:57493:4"/>it is there ſaid, <hi>Perſonaliter exiſtentibus in eodem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilio duobus Archiepiſcopis &amp; alys Epiſcopis cum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orundem ſuffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganijs, ſeptem ducibus cum tot comitibus non-nullis, Abatibus cum quam plurimis gregarijs militibus ac cum populi multitudine copioſa in eodem exiſtentibus, votis regis unanimiter conſentientibus praeceptum &amp; Decretum eſt,</hi> &amp;c. And this was no other then was uſuall in other places, for the Layty to be at Councels, and Princes to ſend their Ambaſſadours to be there and to aſſent for them, if they could not be preſent themſelvs.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third Stage or Tract of time, was from the Conqueſt till the dayes of King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, in all which time there was a great conflict betwixt the Common Law and the Popes Cannon Law: For the Conquerour comming in under the Popes Banner, and under it winning that battell of <hi>Haſtings</hi> in <hi>Suſſex,</hi> wherin he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the Kingdome, did ſuffer the Popes Cannon Law to be brought into the Land, which cauſed the Common Law untill the dayes of <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. to ſuffer the fits of an ague; for in the raigne of a ſtout and valiant King the Common Law prevailed, but in the Raigne of a weak King the Cannon Law prevailed. In the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours time, though he admitted the Popes Law, yet, ſaith <hi>Roger of Cheſter, Nullam Pontificis authoritatem in hoc regno ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitti voluit niſi quatenus ipſe aſſenſum praeberet &amp; nil de rebus Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticis diſcerni voluit, niſi ipſe non ſolum intereſſet ſed praefuiſſet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In K. <hi>William Rufus</hi> time, the Cannon Law prevailed more, for that K. making <hi>Anſelme</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> (whom the Arch-biſhop that now is, and other of the Clergy call S. <hi>Anſelme,</hi> though the Records of that time make him a Traytour) He cals a Synod at <hi>London,</hi> takes away the inveſture of Biſhops from the Crown, and brings in a Canonicall Inſtitution and Confirmation of them from the Pope, takes away the marriage of Prieſts, <hi>ipſe</hi> (ſaith <hi>Matthew Paris) ſacerdotibus uxores prohibuit antea non pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquit' Britan.</hi> p. 116, 117, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8, &amp;c.</note> and maketh other conſtitutions much prejudiciall to the Crown and people. And no marvell, for this proud Prelate at his firſt being Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> thus thanks the King for that favour, <hi>Domino Papae debeo obedientiam tibi conſilium</hi>
            </p>
            <p>King <hi>Hen.</hi> 1. his Succeſſor, though he ſtrugled long with <hi>Anſelme,</hi> and wrote ſharpely to Pope <hi>Paſcall,</hi> yet he could not prevaile all the dayes of <hi>Anſelme,</hi> to undoe thoſe decrees
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57493:5"/>at that Synod, but yet after the death of <hi>Anſelme,</hi> to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt his claime to the Inveſture of Biſhops, given to him by the Cannon Law, hee gave the Arch-biſhopricke of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> to <hi>Rodolph</hi> Biſhop of <hi>London; Et illum per annulum &amp; Paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralem Baculum inveſtivit, contra novi concilij ſtatuta,</hi> ſaith <hi>Mat. Paris.</hi> King <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. to the end he might revive the antient Lawes and cuſtomes of the Kingdome, called his common Councell of all his Nobility and Biſhops, at <hi>Claringdon</hi> in <hi>Wilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiere,</hi> where he made divers Conſtitutions, in Reverſall of thoſe made by <hi>Anſelme,</hi> theſe (<hi>Tho. Becket,</hi> whom this King had made Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> from the meane ſonne of a Jew) traiterouſly oppoſed, which bred great diſſention in the Kingdome; All the Barons of that councell crying out againſt <hi>Becket,</hi> in theſe words, ſaith <hi>Hovenden, quo progrederis proditor, expecta &amp; audi judicium tuum.</hi> But that valiant King, by the unhappy killing of <hi>Becket,</hi> was quite defeated and ſtript of the fruit and benefit of that Councell, and himſelfe put to a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable pennance, as it is at large deſcribed by <hi>Mat. Paris,</hi> and briefly touched in the caſe of premunire in the <hi>Iriſh</hi> reports,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Paris Rep. ſo.</hi> 91, 192</note> and <hi>Becket</hi> ſhortly after Canonized by the Pope for a Saint. <hi>viz.</hi> 19. <hi>Hen.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>In all King <hi>Johns</hi> time the ſonne of <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. the waters of ſtrife betwixt the King and his Clergy grew to a full ſea, his Kingdome interdited by the Pope, and himſelfe at length for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to ſurrender his Kingdome to the Pope, and his own Clergy joyning with the Pope againſt him: So that all his Raigne, the Common Law was under hatches.</p>
            <p>But in <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. time his ſonne, came the good Statute of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and then thoſe waters mightily abated, and the Clergie were glad to receive all their liberties and Juriſdictions from the <hi>Crowne,</hi> as by graunt from that act of <hi>Parliament;</hi> as appeares in the firſt Chapter of that Stat.
<note place="margin">9 <hi>H.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Conceſſimus Deo &amp; hac praeſenti charta confirmavimus pro nobis &amp; haeredibus noſtris in perpetuum quod Eccleſia Anglicana libera ſit, &amp; habeat omnia jura ſua integra &amp; libertates ſuas illaeſas.</hi> And though it is pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in forme of a Charter, as the manner of penning Acts of Parliament was in thoſe times, yet it was a Statute of the Realme made in full Parliament, by the conſent of the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:57493:5"/>
            <p> And although the Clergy of England were again nibling in the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. yeare of <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. againſt the Common Law,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi> 20 <hi>H.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 9.</note> and would fain have brought in that part of the Canon Law, concerning the legitimation of children borne out of wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke, telling the Peeres of the Realme in the Parliament of <hi>Merton;</hi> that, <hi>Quantum ad ſucceſſionem haereditariam Eccleſia ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les habet pro legitimis,</hi> yet the Earles and Barons would not hearken to them, but, as ſaith that Statute, <hi>Omnes Comites &amp; Barones una voce reſponderunt, quod nolunt leges Angliae mutare, quae hucuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> uſitatae ſunt &amp; approbatae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the latter end of the Raigne of this King the Clergy by helpe of the Pope, got head againe, and the Popes exactions up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Crowne and the peoples liberties (for they alwaies goe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether) were growne intollerable, and divers Legantine Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of <hi>Otho</hi> and <hi>Othobon,</hi> burthenſome to the people were introduced, inſomuch that <hi>Matth. Paris</hi> a poore Monke that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in thoſe dayes and the Popes <hi>Creature,</hi> yet by reaſon of the great oppreſſions which he then ſaw upon this Kingdome, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe.
<note place="margin">Mat. Paris</note> And when all the Peeres and Barons of the Realme, perſwaded this King to reſiſt thoſe incrochments upon him and his people, he out of the poverty and weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his ſpirit, makes them this anſwer; <hi>Nec volo nec audeo domino Papae in aliquibus contradicere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. ſtage or tract of time is from the daies of <hi>Edw.</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">4. Time.</note> to the 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. yeare of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. in which time the common Law began to <hi>Recover</hi> and get ſtrength; in all which time the Clergy could make no Lawes, Cannons or Conſtitutions, but what the common Law did allow.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. by the many confirmations which he made of <hi>M. Chart.</hi> and the many liberties which he granted to his people by the Statutes of 25. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1.33. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. and 34. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. as likewiſe by the ſharpe Laws which he made againſt the Popes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions by the Statute of <hi>Carliel.</hi> 35. of his Raigne, he was for all theſe rightly ſtiled, <hi>vindex Anglicanae libertatis,</hi> in doing thus he ſtrengthened mightily his Prerogative: for Prerogative and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty are inſeperable,
<note place="margin">3. Caroli. <hi>Petition of Right.</hi>
               </note> as King CHARLES truly obſerves in his anſwer to the Petition of Right, that the Prerogative is to maintain the peoples liberty, and their liberty ſtrengtheneth the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57493:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>Prerogative.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ſpeech,</hi> 1607.</note> And King <hi>James</hi> his father, declaring that Kings were given for the welfare of their people hath this paſſage. <hi>If you be rich, I can never be poore, and if you be happy, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not chooſe but he fortunate,</hi> &amp;c. And theſe obſervations proved true, and were fulfilled in this King: For never any Prince, either before or after him was more victorious and ſucceſſefull then himſelfe, through the riches and wellfare of his people; who upon all occaſions aided him in his warres with their purſes and fought his battels in their perſons.</p>
            <p>Till the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. yeare of this King, the Clergy had no juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in Eccleſiaſticall cauſes properly allowed to them, but in cauſes of Matrimony and Teſtament, as may appeare by <hi>Fitz. Nat. Bre. Fo.</hi> 41. and by divers Records, which I have ſeen about the beginning of this Kings time. But in the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. year of this King came the ſtatute of <hi>Circumſpectè agatis,</hi> wherin they had Conuſans of many more things, as may appeare by that Law, and though before this time they did attempt to put in ure their owne Conſtitutions, yet the Judges being at that time ſtout and reſolute, alwaies ſent out Prohibitions, as may appeare by the Preamble of the Statute. <hi>Rex talibus Judicibus ſalutem, circumspectè agatis de negotijs tangent: Epiſcopum Norwici &amp; eius Clerum non puniendo eos ſi placitum tenuerint in Curia Chriſtianitatis de his quae ſunt merè ſpiritualia vix,</hi> &amp;c. and there reckons the particular things they ſhall hold plea of, and of no more, and although it mentioneth only the Biſhop of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich,</hi> who was in thoſe dayes the moſt pragmaticall Biſhop for the power of the Church, yet doth that Statute extend to all the Biſhops of the land, and is ſo reſolved in <hi>Plats caſe, Plo. Com. fol.</hi> 36. b. And although this be ſet downe in <hi>Lindwoods Provincials,</hi> to be onely an ordinance of the Church; which was the cauſe, that the Gentleman under the Gallery ſaid it was only an ordinance of the Church; yet the truth is it was an Act of Parliament, as may appeare by the Statute of 2. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. <hi>Cap.</hi> 13. Where it is expreſſely called a Statute, and ſo it is likewiſe reſolved in the 4. <hi>rep. Palmers</hi> caſe, and in the 5. <hi>report, Jefferies</hi> caſe.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Edw.</hi> 2. time, the Clergy by petition to the King (but not otherwiſe) got juriſdiction in many other Cauſes not ſpecified
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57493:6"/>in the Statute of <hi>Circumspectè agatis,</hi> as you may ſee in the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of <hi>Articuli Cleri.</hi> made 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Edw.</hi> 2. too long to remember. Theſe two Statutes were ſo pretious with the Clergy, that they are inſerted <hi>verbatim</hi> in the <hi>Provinciall</hi> Conſtitutions of <hi>Lind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> as the maine part of the Church law, as in truth it is.</p>
            <p>In King <hi>Edward.</hi> 3. time, the Clergy got further Juriſdiction in 9. particular points not formerly graunted to them, as may appeare by the Parliament of 25. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. called <hi>Statutum pro Clero,</hi> a Statute which I have ſome cauſe to remember. It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares in the Parliament roll of that Statute, upon what ground they demanded thoſe priviledges which the King then graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them, not out of right, but by an humble ſupplication to the King, in theſe words mentioned in the Roll being in French, That <hi>pur breverence de dien &amp; de S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Eſglis &amp; de ſa benignity,</hi> he would graunt them all thoſe liberties they petitioned for.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Henry</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. time, the Clergy got ſome power with that King, and made a Conſtitution, called <hi>constitutio Tho. Arundel contra Hereticos,</hi> but this Conſtitution they never durſt put in ure, till they had <hi>coloured</hi> it with that bloody Statute of 2. <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>Cap.</hi> 15. called <hi>Statutum ex officio,</hi> which in truth was no Statute, as may appeare by the Parliament Roll which I have, 2. <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. <hi>tit.</hi> 48. being ſtiled; <hi>petitio Cleri contra Hereticos.</hi> And where it is ſaid in the Act <hi>praelati: &amp; clerus ſupradicti, ac etiam co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitates dicti regni ſupplicarunt,</hi> theſe words <hi>ac etiam comuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes dicti regni,</hi> are not in the Parliament Roll, and ſo was the truth, that the Commons did never aſſent to that Act, as may appeare likewiſe by the Latine Act printed in Linwood. For whereas the Act runnes in this forme of words; <hi>Qui quidem dominus Rex ex aſſenſu Magnatum &amp; aliorum Procerum ejuſdem regni;</hi> &amp;c. <hi>conceſſit &amp; statuis,</hi> &amp;c. there is no mention at all of the Commons, and therefore to helpe this, the words of <hi>aliorum procerum</hi> are thus rendred in the Engliſh Statute now in print (and other diſcreet men of the kingdome) whereby are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed the Commons, and whereby hundreds of Martyrs were cruelly put to death by miſtaken law,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> N. Br. <hi>de He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burend</hi> fo. 170.</note> of which greevance the Commons from time to time complained in ſundry Parliaments, and never reſted till that bloody Statute was hereupon quite re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked by the Stat. of 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. and the oath <hi>ex officio,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:57493:7"/>which had his originall from that cruell Statute quite taken away.</p>
            <p>In the daies of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. in that famous caſe of <hi>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Horſey</hi> and <hi>George Hunne,</hi> mentioned in 7. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>Kelwayes rep.</hi> 182. It was reſolved by a kind of Committee of both houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at <hi>Black-Friers,</hi> at which the King and all his ſpirituall and temporall Councell were preſent (as it ſeemes by that booke) where it was reſolved that no Eccleſiaſticall lawes did bind the people, but what they aſſented unto.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> And now I come to the 5<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> and laſt ſtage or tract of time. <hi>viz.</hi> 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. untill this very time. The Stat. of 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 19. I hold to be nothing els but a declaration of what the Common law was before, and not introductive of a new law, which is the reaſon, as I conceive, that the Statute is penned in negative words, that they ſhall not make Conſtitutions and Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons without the Kings aſſent, which may be interpreted his aſſent in Parliament, as well as his aſſent and confirmation by his letters Pattents.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That they ſhall not make Cannons contrary to the Kings Prerogative, the Lawes, Cuſtomes and Statutes of the land, now what can they tell what is the Kings Prerogative, the Laws and Cuſtomes of the Realme, unleſſe the Laity who have more skill then they, to judge of thoſe things, do give their aſſent. And that this ſeems to be the meaning of that Act, that the Parliament ſhould have a power in eſtabliſhing the Canons of the Clergie, it appeares by that Act in the appointing of the 32. Commiſſioners for the making of Canons; whereof 16. were to be taken from the Temporalitie out of the upper and nether Houſe of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and 16. more were to be taken from the Clergy. So that the Clergie had not that power to do it alone, without the Laity, though they had the Kings Royall aſſent thereunto.</p>
            <p>And that the practiſe was alwaies ſo, that the Acts and Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of the Clergy had their determination and concluſion in Parliament, appeares by theſe examples.</p>
            <p>The 6 Articles mentioned in the Stat.
<note place="margin">31. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 14.</note> 31. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. were debated in the Synod or Convocation of the Clergy, but were not binding to the people without confirmation in Parliament, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares clearly by that Act.
<note place="margin">32. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 26.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The inſtitution of a Chriſtian man compiled in a book by all
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57493:7"/>the Clergy of England, containing matter of doctrine, as likewiſe the Rites and Ceremonies of the Church were not binding to the people without the approbation and confirmation of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 26. as appears by that Statute.</p>
            <p>And whereas it was ſaid under the Gallery, that the Laietie have nothing to do to meddle with matter of Religion. If he had pleaſed to have caſt his eyes upon the Stat. of 1. <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. <hi>ca.</hi> 1. he would have found there a notable debate and diſpute in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by the Laitie onely againſt Tranſubſtantiation,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>m l.</hi> 5 In S <hi>Th. Cottons</hi> library.</note> and Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in one kinde, as may appeare in that Statute. Beſides I have ſeene the Diary of King <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. written with his owne hand, wherein he hath this paſſage, <hi>This day there was a notable debate in the Lower Houſe of Parliament against the Communion in one kinde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So the Statutes of 2. <hi>E.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. and 5. <hi>E.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing marriage of Prieſts, gave a finall determination to that point, by a binding Law upon a debate had firſt in the Convocation. The Canons and Conſtitutions made by the 32. Commiſſioners upon the Statutes of 27. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 15.35. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 16. and 3. <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 11. were compiled 6. <hi>E.</hi> 6. and afterwards printed and publiſhed, and all the Commiſſioners names I have ſeen under king <hi>E.</hi> 6. own hand: and although they be ſingular good Laws, and written in excellent language, yet becauſe they have not had the allowance of Parliament, are not received as binding Laws at this day.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the 39. Articles of Religion, made in the Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion 1562. were not binding Laws to the whole Kingdome, till they had their approbation and confirmation, by the Stat. of 13. <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 12. Thus have I as briefly as I could, run over the practiſe of all ages in making Eccleſiaſticall Laws, and the reaſons of their practiſe are briefly theſe,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>A comparatis,</hi> by an argument <hi>a minori ad majus,</hi> If property of goods cannot be taken from me without my aſſent in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is the fundamentall Law of the land, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in the petition of right, why then property and liberty of Conſcience which is much greater, as much as <hi>bona animi</hi> are above <hi>bona fortunae,</hi> cannot be taken from me without my aſſent.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Libertie of Religion and Conſcience, are as I take it, within the words of <hi>magna Charta,</hi>
               <note place="margin">M <hi>Ch. cap.</hi> 29.</note> graunted to me as mine Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, <hi>cap.</hi> 29. <hi>Nullus liber homo impriſonetur aut diſſeiſetur de
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57493:8"/>libertatibus vel liberis conſuetudinibus ſuis,</hi> And liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is the greateſt liberty.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> It is by a neceſſary Conſequence and deduction within the words <hi>Impriſonetur:</hi> for put the Caſe that the Clergy make Cannons to which I never aſſented, and I breake theſe Cannons, whereupon I am excommunicated, and upon a <hi>ſignificavit</hi> by the Biſhop, my body is taken and impriſoned by a writ <hi>de ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicato capiendo,</hi> now ſhall I lye in priſon all the dayes of my life, and ſhall never be delivered by a <hi>Cautione admittenda,</hi> unleſſe I will come in, <hi>&amp; parere mandatis Eccleſiae,</hi> which are point blank againſt my conſcience.</p>
            <p>And thus have I proved the firſt and chiefeſt point, that no Cannons can bind the Laiety and Clergy, without conſent in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament: and therfore theſe Cannons made againſt the Laiety, as well as the Clergy, without their aſſent, cannot bind.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Point. </seg>2</label> I come now to the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. point, which is this, Admitting the Clergy have power to make Cannons without common aſſent, The queſtion is, whether they had lawfull authority to make theſe by force of the Stat. of 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 19. I thinke they had not.</p>
            <p>The words of the Statute by which the Clergy have power to make Cannons,
<note place="margin">25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 19.</note> are penned in the negative: That they ſhall not enact, promulge or execute any Cannons or Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in their Convocations, and which alwayes ſhall be aſſembled by authority of the Kings writ, unleſſe the ſame Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy may have the Kings moſt royall aſſent, to make, promulge and execute ſuch Cannons upon, paine of impriſonment, and to make fine at the Kings will.</p>
            <p>By which it plainly appeares, that the Clergy have no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to make Cannons but in their Convocation, and that to the making of theſe Cannons, there muſt be the Kings royall aſſent.</p>
            <p>Whether this were ſo or no, comes now to be examined, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is to be obſerved, the ſeverall writs and Commiſſions which they had for the making of theſe Cannons.</p>
            <p>The firſt writ that iſſued forth,
<note place="margin">About the firſt of Feb. 1639.</note> was the Parliament writ, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to every Biſhop, for calling them and their Clergy, which had this clauſe in the latter end, <hi>Ad conſentiendum ijs quae tunc
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57493:8"/>ibidem de communi concilio regni noſtri divina favente clementia con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigerint ordinari.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 20. of February following went foorth two Writs more, called the Convocation Writs, directed to the ſeverall Arch-biſhops of <hi>Canterbury</hi> and <hi>Yorke,</hi> for the election of Clerks to the ſeverall Convocations, which had theſe words in the writs, <hi>Ad tractandum, conſentiendum &amp; concludendum ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per praemiſſis &amp; alijs quae ſibi clarius exponentur tunc ex parte noſtra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Parliament began the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>Aprill</hi> following, and on the 15. of <hi>Aprill</hi> iſſued out a Commiſſion to the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> to alter, amend and change the old Canons, and to make new during the Parliament; the like went to the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Yorke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the fift of May following, the Parliament was diſſolved, wherby, as I conceive the Law to be the Convocation was likewiſe diſſolved and determined, which being ſo, and no Cannons made by them all this time, then could there be no Cannons made in the Convocation, according to the words of the Statute. And therfore the 12. of May following there went foorth another Commiſſion to the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> to make Cannons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> during the Kings will and pleaſure, with a proviſo contained in the ſaid Commiſſion, that the ſaid Cannons ſhould not be repugnant to the Rubricks in the booke of common-Prayer, the 39. Articles, nor to the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, order and Ceremonies of the Church,</hi> The like Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion went to the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Yorke.</hi> In which Commiſſion of 12. May, there was an expreſſe Revocation and making void of the Commiſſion of 15<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Aprilis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that the Commiſſion of 15. <hi>Aprilis</hi> being determined in Law by the Parliament, to which it referred, as likewiſe by the Commiſſion of 12. May, which abſolutely revoked it. All the Cannons that were made, and now printed were made out of Parliament, and ſo conſequently out of Convocation, and meerly by the Commiſſion of 12. May.</p>
            <p>The 30. <hi>June</hi> following, comes the Kings Letters <hi>Patents</hi> of Confirmation of theſe Canons made by the Commiſſion of 12. <hi>Maij,</hi> in which Letters Patents, he doth in expreſſe words
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57493:9"/>both give his Royall aſſent to the Cannons, and ratifies and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes them according to that forme of the ſaid Statute or Act of <hi>Parliament</hi> of 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. Now that Statute doth only give power to the King to aſſent unto and confirm Cannons made in Convocation, and therfore there being no Cannons made in Convocation but afterward, the aſſent and confirmation of things not then in being muſt needs be void; for in our Law, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmare</hi> is <hi>firmum facere,</hi> which preſuppoſeth an entity or being of the thing that is to be made firme; for <hi>ex nihilo non fit quid,</hi> ſaith the Philoſopher. And therefore the foundation fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, on which the confirmation ſhould worke, doth cauſe it therby to be abſolutely void; according to that rule of Law, <hi>Sublato fundamento deſtruitur opus.</hi> And ſo I conclude this ſecond point alſo, that the Authority which ſhould give life and being to theſe Cannons is void in Law.</p>
            <p>The third and laſt point is this,
<note place="margin">Point.</note> admitting that the Clergy had power and lawfull authority to make theſe Cannons, whether the ſaid Cannons be not void in Law for the matter contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in them, and I thinke they are in that they are againſt the Lawes and Statutes of the Realme, and ſo contrary to the laid proviſo in the Statute of 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>In the debate wherof I will firſt conſider of the Cannons, <hi>primae Claſſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Of the Oath contained in the ſixt Cannon.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Of the Benevolence granted by the Clergy, and contained in the ſecond booke of Cannons, all which I ſhall hold to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Laws and Statutes of the Realme.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Concerning the firſt I will only inſiſt upon three Cannons, for the reſt have bin fully ſpoken too, <hi>viz,</hi> 1, 12, and 13. Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons.</p>
            <p>For the firſt Cannon in making determinations concerning Royall power and property of goods, they have done againſt Law, and have medled with things of which they have no Conuſans, for the expoſition of them belongs to the Judges of the Land, and they have no more right to expound them, then the Judges have to expound Texts of Scripture. And therefore it was aptly ſpoken by the Atturney generall in <hi>Harriſons</hi> caſe, who was indited in the Kings-Bench, <hi>Trin.</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:57493:9"/>14. <hi>Car.</hi> for calling Judge <hi>Hutton</hi> Traitor, who there ſaid that it was his opinion, and the opinion of all <hi>Orthodox</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, that if the King thought he might with a ſafe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience take my goods, I was to let him have them, and it was high Treaſon in me to deny him or make reſiſtance; To whom the Atturney generall replyed in theſe words, that the Prerogative of the King, and liberty of the Subject were given and defended by the Laws of the Realme, and that the Judges were the expounders of that Prerogative: And though the Clergy of England do ſeeme in this Cannon to maintaine this abſolute power, yet wee muſt know that the Kings of England never made Title to governe by it: For though king <hi>James</hi> in his book of free Monarchies dives further in this point then any before him; yet he determines it thus, that this ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute power is onely between God and him, not in relation to his people in point of their government; for the ſame King ſaith in another place, that a Subject of England may chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge the King in the ſame language, as the poore widdow challenged <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon, Fac iuſtitiam aut ne ſis Rex;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Par ſpeech An.</hi> 1609. A booke condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the fire by both houſes of Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t 7 <hi>lac.</hi>
               </note> and then adds this, That thoſe Kings are either Tyrants or perjured, that govern not according to their Law; and thoſe that perſwade them otherwiſe are vipers and peſts, both to the King and Common-wealth: And I have now in my hand that Kings Proclamation for the ſuppreſſing D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Cowels</hi> booke, called <hi>The interpreter for advancing his abſolute power to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow of all Parliaments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the 12. and 13. Cannons, touching the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and diſcharging of Chancellours and Officials from exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting any Excommunication in his own perſon or any cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure againſt the Clergy, becauſe they are Lay-men, I ſay that in doing and enacting this,
<note place="margin">Stat 29 H 8. c 17.</note> they have done quite contrary to an Act of Parliament ſtill in force, in taking from them this power of exerciſing the cenſures of the Church, which that Statute gives them, which I did looke when ſome Civilians now in the houſe ſhould have maintained: And although it were to be wiſhed that only Clergy men ſhould have this power of Excommunication, and other <hi>Cenſures</hi> of the Church; yet ſeeing an Act of Parliament hath given this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:57493:10"/>to Lay-men: It is a high preſumption in them to make Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons againſt it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Concerning the Oath mentioned in the 6 Cannon, two things fall into queſtion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether the Clergy can impoſe a new Oath? I thinke they cannot; For I hold it for a ground in Law, that no Oath can be impoſed upon the Subject, but what is warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted either by the cuſtome of the Realme, which is no other then the common Law, or els by ſome Act of Parliament to warrant it: And herein the Clergy hath done more then the King doth at this day by his <hi>Prerogative</hi> Royall, by which he governes his people, and is part of the common Law, and differs no more from it, then <hi>pars à toto,</hi> called by <hi>Bracton privilegium Regis,</hi> by the Sta. of <hi>Weſt.</hi> 1. <hi>Droit du Roy,</hi> by the Regiſter, <hi>Jus regium Coronae.</hi> Now the King doth not by his Prerogative in any of his Commiſſions or Letters patents, which are of greater force then Cannons, impoſe an Oath without ſome Act of Parliament to warrant it; As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, by the Commiſſion of <hi>Sewers</hi> there is power to give an Oath, but that is warranted by the Sta. of 23. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. The Commiſſion of Bankrupts gives an Oath, but that is backed by the Statutes of 13. <hi>Elizab. Cap.</hi> 13. and 21. <hi>Jaco.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So the Commiſſion of <hi>Charitable uſes</hi> is warranted to give Oathes by the Stat. of 43. <hi>Eliz.</hi> many more inſtances might be given, which I omit.</p>
            <p>Nay the Oathes we take to the King, concerning his Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, and our own allegiance, to which we are tied by a bond of nature, as his Liege people, yet for the impoſing of theſe two Oathes, there are two Acts of Parliament provided, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 1. &amp; 3. <hi>Jaco. c.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>Beſides, the Clergy have no power by the Sta. of 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. which gives them power to make Cannons and Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titutions to impoſe Oathes; for an Oath is no Cannon or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, but a meere Collaterall thing; juſt as if they ſhould have enjoyned a man to have entred into a bond of a 1000. pound to have obſerved their Cannons, this had beene void, and a prohibition had lyen at the common Law for it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57493:10"/>this is a Collaterall thing, and a charge upon my goods, and ſo is an Oath upon my conſcience, and therefore in preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing an Oath by vertue of their 6 Cannon, they have exceeded their authority.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond thing is, whether the matter of the Cannons be good.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Concerning the matter of the Oath contained in the ſixt Cannon; divers exceptions have beene taken by thoſe lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Gentlemen that have argued before, which I will not remember, but adde foure which have not beene yet ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken too.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Exception</hi> is in theſe words, <hi>That I will not indeavour by my ſelfe or any other to bring in any Popiſh Doctrine, contrary to that which is ſo eſtabliſhed,</hi> now <hi>That,</hi> and <hi>So,</hi> being words of Relation do referre to the next Antecedent, being <hi>(Popiſh Doctrine)</hi> not mentioned in any part of the Oath before: So that, <hi>reddendo ſingula ſingulis,</hi> it runnes thus in ſence and in <hi>Conſtruction, I will not indeavour my ſelfe to bring in any Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Doctrine,</hi> contrary to that Popiſh Doctrine which is ſo eſtabliſhed, <hi>Ergo,</hi> ſome Popiſh Doctrine is eſtabliſhed by the Church of England. This conſtruction was ſo evident and plaine to them, that for the curing therof, though this Oath with the word <hi>(Popiſh)</hi> in it, and the reſt of the Cannons were confirmed by the Kings letters Patents 30. <hi>Iunij</hi> 16. <hi>Car.</hi> yet 5<hi rend="sup">to</hi>. <hi>Julij</hi> after, they got a Commiſſion from the King, to give this Oath, leaving out the word <hi>Popiſh,</hi> whereby they have made the remedy worſe then the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, by giving an Oath which was never confirmed by the King.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond <hi>Exception</hi> is in theſe words, <hi>Nor will I ever give my conſent to alter the government of this Church by Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, Biſhops, Deanes and Arch-Deacons,</hi> &amp;c. which I may fitly call a Covenant againſt the Kings ſupremacy, which I thus make good.</p>
            <p>It is a part of my Oath of <hi>Supremacy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Stat.</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 1.</note> that I ſhall aſſiſt the King in all preheminences and juriſdictions belonging to his <hi>Crowne.</hi> Now it is a part of his juriſdiction to alter this government by his Parliament, and to appoint and eſtabliſh
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57493:11"/>another, which if he ſhall be ſo minded to doe, I am by this Oath not to aſſiſt him in it, I am not ſo much as to give my aſſent; wherby I doe unavoidably fall upon this Rock, that for the ſaving of my oath, I muſt deny my obedience to the King,
<note place="margin">Azor. de juramento.</note> or by obeying the King I muſt fall upon per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury: For though it be true, as the Cannoniſts ſay, that when a Law is changed to which I am bound by oath: Though, I am thereby materially diſcharged; yet formally I am bound in reſpect of my will: For if ever I actually aſſent to the altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I am really perjured.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third <hi>Exception</hi> is in theſe words, <hi>I will not conſent to alter the government of this Church, by Arch-biſhops,</hi> &amp;c. as <hi>it ſtands now establiſhed, and as by right it ought to ſtand;</hi> now to ſpeake properly, there is no government of this Church of <hi>England</hi> by <hi>Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, Deanes, Arch-Deacons,</hi> &amp;c. but only by the King, and they governe onely by and under him. And why the King ſhould be quite left out, ſeems a thing ſtrange to me, unleſſe they will ſay he is comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded within the <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which is a moſt unworthy place for ſo great a Majeſty.</p>
            <p>And that the Clergy had ſome ill meaning in this omiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the King out of this Oath, I have ſome reaſon more then to ſuſpect, when I caſt my eye upon ſome dangerous paſſages that are in their writings about the Kings Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, advancing it higher then the King himſelfe would have them, touching the Subjects property of goods, but depreſſing it too low concerning his Eccleſiaſticall power. And this appeared lately before us by a very dangerous ſpeech of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d.</hi> D. <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels</hi> book <hi>verbo</hi> Par. liament ſuppr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſed by K <hi>Iams</hi> Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly printed without authority.</note> 
               <hi>Coſins,</hi> who ſaid that the King ought not to be called <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame head of the Church,</hi> and ſeemed to colour it by Biſhop <hi>Iewels</hi> opinion, which is moſt falſe. For the Act of 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Eliz.</hi> Revives all the Statutes of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. touching Supreame head of the Church: So that the King may as well be called Supreame head of the Church on Earth (for ſo are the words of the Statute of 26. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 37. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 17.) as ſupreame go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour. Beſides the diſtinction that he uſed in this place, That Biſhops had their juriſdiction from God, <hi>ratione officij,</hi> but <hi>ratione exercitij,</hi> they had it from the King, which is both abſurd and erronious.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:57493:11"/>
            <p> It is abſurd, for he will not allow that Biſhops and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſhould be all one, but by this diſtinction they ſhould, for neither of them can exerciſe their functions, but by permiſſion from the King.</p>
            <p>It is erronious, for I doe not only ſay it, but will proove it, that Biſhops have no juriſdiction here, but from the King; for it is a knowne diſtinction among the Cannoniſts (as that learned Civilian that ſpake laſt doth well know) That in a Biſhop there is a double power
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Poteſtas ordinis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Potestas Juriſdictionis.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Poteſtas ordinis,</hi> to preach, to baptize, to adminiſter the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> this power is <hi>iure divino,</hi> agreeable with all other Miniſters.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Poteſtas Juriſdictionis,</hi> as to admit, inſtitute, and give mandates, to induct into Church-livings, to keepe Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Courts, to call Sinods, to viſit Churches: For which two latter we pay Sinodals and procurations to this day, and which if the ancient forme were obſerved, would be of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent uſe at this day, for the depriving of <hi>Arminians,
<note place="margin">D <hi>Bois</hi> Deane of <hi>Cant:</hi> in a vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tation Sermon.</note> Socinians</hi> and other Hereticks; but as a learned Prelate writes, they are now become, <hi>Nummorum non morum viſitationes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This power of <hi>Iuriſdiction,</hi> ſay the Cannoniſts, is, <hi>de iure humano,</hi> and from the Pope, for ſo is their rule, <hi>Epiſcopi de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendunt à Papa tanquam membra à capite;</hi> we in our Law ſay, that their juriſdiction is wholy from the King, and ſo it is acknowledged by themſelves in expreſſe words in the Act of Parliament of 37. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 17. an act in force at this day; <hi>That Arch-biſhops, Biſhops,</hi> &amp;c. and all other Eccleſiaſticall perſons have no manner of Eccleſiaſticall juriſdiction, but by, from and under the King.</p>
            <p>Nay this power in Biſhops to excommunicate is a power of juriſdiction and derived to them from the Pope ſay the Canoniſts,
<note place="margin">Azorua Lanelot. Inſtit Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris can.</note> We ſay in our Law that they have this power from the King, for though Kings cannot excommunicate <hi>miniſterialiter,</hi> by reaſon they are Lay-perſons, as ſaith <hi>Bracton, l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 8. yet they may do it <hi>authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative,</hi> by reaſon of their office by Commiſſion from them, Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe let any man tell me how Judges Delegate do at this day excommunicate but by Commiſſion from the King grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:57493:12"/>the Statutes of 24. H. 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. and 25. H. 8. <hi>cap;</hi> 19. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> how doth the high Commiſſion at this day excommunicate, but by the like authority grounded upon the Statute of 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore I do conclude this third exception that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ing the Clergy doe ſeem by this Oath to derive their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on by any other right then from the King, they have hereby mightily intrenched upon the Kings <hi>Prerogative.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth and laſt exception to the Oath i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in theſe words, <hi>Nor ſhall you ever ſubject it</hi> (meaning the Church of England) to <hi>the uſurpations and ſuperſtitions of the Sea of Rome,</hi> and doth not ſay the Church of Rome, wherby it containes <hi>a negative Pregnant;</hi> That is to ſay, you may not ſubject the Church of England to the ſuperſtitions and uſurpations of the Sea of Rome; but you may ſubject it to the uſurpations and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions of the Church of Rome: Now there is as much diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt the Sea of Rome, and the Church of Rome, as betwixt Treaſon and Treſpaſſe; and this appears plainly by the Statute of 23<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Eliza. cap.</hi> 1. where it is ſaid, that to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to the Sea of Rome is Treaſon, but to be reconciled to the Church of Rome is not Treaſon, for then every Papiſt in England ſhould be a Traitour, being a member of that Church, and therfore reconciled to it. Now the Sea of Rome is nothing elſe but the Papacy or <hi>Supremacy of the Pope,</hi> wherby by vertue of the Cannon, <hi>unam ſanctam,</hi> made by Pope <hi>Boneface</hi> the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. he challengeth a ſuperiority of Juriſdiction and correction over all Kings and Princes upon Earth; and thoſe perſons which take the <hi>Iuramentum fidei,</hi> contained in the end of ſome of the editions, that I have ſeen of <hi>the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Trent,</hi> which acknowledgeth this Supremacy, are ſaid to be reconciled to the Sea of Rome.</p>
            <p>The Church of Rome is nothing elſe but a number of men within the Popes dominions, or elſe where, profeſſing the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of Popery; and that the Clergy had an ill meaning in leaving this clauſe in the Oath thus looſe, I have ſome reaſon to imagine, when I finde in their late books, that they ſay the Church of Rome is a true Church, and Salvation is to be had in it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Concerning the Benevolence of 6. ſubſidies granted by
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:57493:12"/>the Clergy, I will ſpeake but a word, becauſe I have trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled you too long: It is not a Subſidy, for then it ſhould have bin by the Convocation during Parliament, as the books are, 1. <hi>Hen.</hi> 7.21. <hi>Edw.</hi> 4. &amp; 28. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. and as the uſe is at this day to paſſe in the Acts of Subſidy.</p>
            <p>But it is called a Benevolence or free gift, and yet if any refuſe to pay it, he ſhall be deprived, which is a very Bull; for if men be compelled to pay it, how can it be ſaid to be a free gift: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the King was not well dealt with, as I conceive in paſſing his letters Patents of confirmation of this Benevolence, dated 3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> 16. <hi>Carol.</hi> For upon a ſignification of his Majeſties pleaſure by the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> the Docket is to this effect drawn up, May it pleaſe your Majeſty, this doth contain your acceptance of this benevolence, and your confirmation of the ſame; and yet there is a clauſe in the letters Patents not mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the King in the Docket,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>id.</hi> the Dock.</note> wherby the Clergy have power to make Cannons and decrees, compelling the payment of the ſame upon paine of deprivation, and ſo they did againſt all Law to annex deprivation to offences of ſuch a nature,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Miniſt. Eccleſitit.</hi> 8.</note> when as by the late excellent Lawes of Reformation, <hi>leg. Eccleſiaſt. tit. de Deprivati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one,</hi> Miniſters are not to be deprived, but <hi>propter horrenda flagitia,</hi> and ſo ſaith <hi>Duarenus</hi> an excellent <hi>Civilian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo M. <hi>Speaker,</hi> I have done with the Cannons, and conclude that they are illegall. 1. In point of originall Juriſdiction. 2. In point of <hi>Derivative authority.</hi> 3. In the matter and form of them, or more briefly in the language of the Schooles, they are illegall and void, <hi>in toto &amp; in qualibet parte.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:57493:13"/>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:57493:13"/>
            <head>THE SECOND ARGVMENT <hi>CONCERNING</hi> THE PREMVNIRE.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>March</hi> 2. 1640.</note>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. SPEAKER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am by the order of the Houſe to ſpeak this day of the penalty which the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy by making their late Cannons in their late convention, rather then Synod have forfeited and encurred: The time before I debated the illegallity of thoſe Cannons, that was <hi>de culpâ;</hi> this diſpute is <hi>de panâ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Illegall faults draw after them legall puniſhments: For there are no veniall ſinnes at the common Law; I was long in the debate of the Cannons, and I feare that the weightineſſe of this diſpute concerning the pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, will make me runne into the ſame errour. I was doubtfull at firſt what puniſhment I ſhould fixe upon the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy: but conſidering the vote of this Houſe, that the late
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:57493:14"/>Cannons were againſt the Kings Prerogative royall, the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall Lawes of the Land, the liberty of the Subject, and divers Acts of Parliament, I ſetled my reſolutions. There is a rule in the Schooles, that <hi>potentes potenter punientan,</hi> great offenders ſhall receive great puniſhments; The Engliſh in ſhort is this, I hold they have encurred a <hi>Premunire,</hi> viz. All <hi>Arch-hiſhops, Biſhops, Deanes, Arch-deacons,</hi> &amp;c. which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the making of them; which that I may diſtinctly and clearly prove, I will divide all that I have to ſay upon this matter into 4. parts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What a Premunire is.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The originall ground and cauſe of a Premunire.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The grounds and reaſons in Law why the Clergy have in this caſe incurred a Premunire.</p>
            <p n="4">4. An Anſwer to the Objections that are made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Premunire; eſpecially by three Civilians now in print.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Concerning the firſt, it is a rule taken by that excellent Oratour,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cic.</hi> 1. <hi>offic.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>omnis rei inſtitutio à definitione proficiſcitur,</hi> hee that would handle a thing fully muſt define it true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            <p>Now a Premunire takes its name from the words of the Writ called <hi>Premu:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>V. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>br.</hi> 152.</note> 
               <hi>facias,</hi> about the end of the Writ, <hi>videlicet, Praecipimus tibi, quod per bonos &amp; legales homines de balliva tua premu: facias,</hi> J. D. <hi>&amp; Abettores ſuos,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>qd. ſint coram no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis à die paſche in quindecim dies,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ad reſpondend. nobis de contemptu,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in exhaeredationis Coronae noſtrae periculum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestum,</hi> which is in ſence and meaning, though not ſo ſtrong and ſignificant as <hi>praemonere facias;</hi> For the expounders of the Civill and Cannon Lawes confound both words ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Proverbe, premoniti ſunt premuniti.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this Writ of <hi>praemu.</hi> is better underſtood by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes on which the ſame is founded, <hi>viz.</hi> 25. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 22. <hi>&amp;</hi> 27. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>de proviſoribus,</hi> 16 <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. which Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes were made for the correction of the incroachment of the Pope and his Clergy upon the Crown and Laws of England, Upon all which Statutes and bookes of Law, I thus define a <hi>praemu.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:57493:14"/>
            <p> A <hi>praemu.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Definition</note> is a defence of the Crown and Laws of the Land from the tyrrany and oppreſſion of ſpirituall Juriſdiction, either forraine in the Pope, taken away by the Stat. of 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> or at home by the Clergy in the Eccleſiaſticall Courts, wherby is incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red this penalty of being put out of the Kings Protection, loſſe of lands and goods, and perpetuall impriſonment.</p>
            <p>This may ſeeme a ſharpe and ſevere puniſhment to be inflicted on Clergy men, but when the reaſons and grounds of Law are conſidered, and how the Kings of <hi>England</hi> were neceſſitated to it, the ſharpnes of the puniſhment will not ſeem ſtrange to any, which is the ſecond head of my diviſion, and which I now come unto.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Concerning the originall cauſe and ground of the <hi>praemu.</hi> it ariſeth from the oppoſition and Antipathy betwixt the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and the Cannon Law, or the Law of God, and the Law of the Pope; the Common Law being derived from the one, and the Cannon Law from the other, which makes the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition as great, as betwixt CHRIST and Antichriſt, which hath in all ages (as I could ſhew you) cauſed a hatred of our Law, and of the profeſſours therof, from the Clergy and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours of the Cannon Law.</p>
            <p>And that this may not ſeeme ſtrange, I will very briefly in honour to the Common Law, prove and maintaine that it is deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the Law of GOD, and is the neareſt unto it of any Law in the world, which King <hi>James</hi> hath largely prooved in a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Speech of his, 1607. but yet I will give 2, or 3. inſtances more.</p>
            <p>It is thus ſaid by <hi>Priſet</hi> chiefe Juſtice of the Common-pleas,
<note place="margin">34 <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>f.</hi> 40.</note> 
               <hi>ley denglitre est foundu ſur le ley de dieu,</hi> which being tranſlated out of our Law-French into better Engliſh is thus, the Law of England is founded upon the Law of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ley de tre &amp; ley de dieu ſont,
<note place="margin">7. <hi>H.</hi> 8.191 <hi>Kell.</hi>
                  </note> tout un per Fineux</hi> chiefe Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of England, that is, the Law of God, and the Law of the Land are all one.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pollard</hi> to the ſame purpoſe: But it will be ſaid,
<note place="margin">12. <hi>H.</hi> 8 <hi>f.</hi> 2</note> that this was onely the opinion of Lawyers, and every one will be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to commend his own profeſſion, and therfore I ſhall go much higher.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:57493:15"/>
            <p> In the yeare of CHRIST about 169. <hi>Lucius</hi> a King of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land was the firſt Chriſtian King, and the firſt annointed in all the world, and preſently after he was converted to the Faith, ſought how to governe his people by good Lawes, and fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that the Romane Lawes were then the moſt famous in all the world, ſent by his Letter to <hi>Elutherius</hi> then Biſhop of Rome, for a coppy of thoſe Lawes; that godly Biſhop (for ſo the Biſhops of Rome then were, and long after) wrote an anſwer of his Letter to this effect, <hi>Petiſtis à nobis leges Romanas vobis tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitti,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>leges Romanas reprobare poſſumus, legem Dei nequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Habetis penes vos in regno utram<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> paginam, ex illis ſume legem, &amp; per illam rege veſtrum Brittanniae Regnum, vica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius enim Dei eſtis in regno,</hi> &amp;c. as may appeare more at large in the Lawes of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Ed. cap.</hi> 17. compiled by <hi>Lambert,</hi> where the letters are ſet downe at large; and therfore King <hi>James</hi> had good cauſe to ſay, That the Lawes of <hi>England</hi> were framed as neare as could be to the Judiciall Lawes of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this affinity which our Law hath to the Law of GOD, hath beene the cauſe (as I conceive) of that contention be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt our Law and the Canon Law, which hath beene like to that of <hi>Hagar</hi> contending with her Miſtris, and hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved divers times the ſame doome, <hi>Caſt out the bond-woman and her ſonne,</hi> as I could proove by many preſidents, which for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity I omit. And as the contention and oppoſition increaſed, ſo did the puniſhment, as may appeare in theſe foure parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt puniſhment upon the Clergy was prohibition onely.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond was, a prohibition with a pain.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third was, by fine and impriſonment.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth and laſt (when none of the reſt would do good) was by a Premunire and there it ended.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the firſt, It is obſervable that the firſt newes of the Canon Law here in England, was, <hi>Anno</hi> 1150. xvj. <hi>Steph. Reg.</hi> compiled by <hi>Gratian,</hi> and called the Popes Decrees, but came to us here in England by a wile, under another name, called <hi>Rogationes,</hi> and intreated to be received of us under the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:57493:15"/>pretext of Holineſſe, becauſe of the faſting and Ember-dayes, tending to faſting and prayer, which thoſe Lawes ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contained, and hence the Ember before Whit-ſuntide is called the Rogation weeke from that name: But King <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi> finding them pernicious to the native Laws of England, gave them this welcome and entertainment, for faith <hi>Roger Bacon, Rex Stephanus allatis legibus Italiae</hi> (meaning the Cannon Lawes) <hi>publico edicto prohibuit ne ab aliquo retine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. When this prohibition would doe no good, but other Cannon Lawes were thruſt upon us in the time of <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. as the Decretall Epiſtles, under Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the ninth, from which that flaming Law of burning Hereticks was firſt hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, a ſharper puniſhment was deviſed by <hi>Hen.</hi> 3.19. of his raigne againſt the Civill and Cannon Laws, prohibiting the uſe of them here in England under a ſevere pain, as Laws that were derogatory to the ſupreame Majeſty and independancy of the Crowne of England.</p>
            <p n="3">3. After theſe Decretals, the Extravigants of <hi>Boneface</hi> the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. were brought into this Kingdome, which were ſo inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to the Soveraignty of Kings, that whoſoever ſhall but reade one of thoſe Lawes, called <hi>unam Sanctam,</hi> will ſay that either a King of England muſt lay downe his Crowne, or quite abandon thoſe Lawes: Whereupon <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. taking care to preſerve the Crowne and the liberties of his people, did in the third and ſixt yeare of his Raigne iſſue out divers Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, to enquire of the Juriſdiction of the Clergy,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fitz.</hi> N. B. 40.</note> which at that time was limited chiefly to matters of Matrimony and Teſtament, untill the Stat. of 13. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. called <hi>Circumspectè agatis,</hi> inlarged their power and Juriſdiction in many more particulars.</p>
            <p>One of thoſe Inquiſitions, <hi>A<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> 6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. I will only menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on inſtead of many, which was taken at <hi>Lawneſton</hi> in <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall</hi> before <hi>Roger Loveday</hi> and <hi>Walter de Wyburne;</hi> Theſe two were to enquire of <hi>Walter</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Exeter,</hi> for drawing the Kings Subjects into his Court, and holding plea, <hi>de debitis &amp; catallis quae non ſunt de Teſtamento &amp; Matrimonio,</hi> and for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them enter into bond and a new Oath, <hi>quod ſibi in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus<pb n="28" facs="tcp:57493:16"/>adharebunt &amp; per omnia</hi> (ſuch another new fangled Oath as was in the late Cannons) and this is in the Record alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to be <hi>in laſionem Coronae, exhaeredationem &amp; depauperationem manifeſtam quae ulterius ſuſtinere nolumus nec debemus,</hi> and it was adjudged that the Biſhop ſhould for this offence, make ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to the King.</p>
            <p n="21">21. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. <hi>Par. Rolls pl.</hi> 17. <hi>m.</hi> 3. <hi>indorſ. Jo:</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Yorke,</hi> excommunicated two of the Biſhops of <hi>Durhams</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, named <hi>William Willicon</hi> and <hi>John Rowman,</hi> for keeping poſſeſſion of ſome of the lands of the Biſhops of <hi>Durham,</hi> to which the Archbiſhop pretended a title. This being a high offence againſt the Stat. of <hi>Circumſpecte agatis,</hi> newly granted to the Clergy but a little before, received this Judgement in Parliament.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the Biſhop ſhould be impriſoned.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Should make a ſubmiſſion to the King, and</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Should pay 4000. Marks fine, which was a mighty ſumme, whenas in thoſe dayes, the price of an Oxe was but 5. <hi>ſh.</hi> as appeares in the end of the 25. <hi>cap.</hi> of the Stat. of <hi>Weſtm'.</hi> 2. made 13. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. <hi>tit. aſſize.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, When the Clergy would take warning by none of theſe examples, the Kings of England were forced to make theſe ſharpe Lawes of Premunire that I mentioned before, and to ſay to them in the language of <hi>Salomon</hi> to rayling <hi>Shimei,</hi> (for ſo was the Cannon Law to the Kings of England:)
<note n="*" place="margin">2 Kin. 2.</note> keepe <hi>at home in your owne place, if once you paſſe over the brooke</hi> Kidron, <hi>your blood be upon your owne head.</hi> So the Kings of England ſpake by their Lawes to the Clergy, <hi>Keepe within your owne bounds, given you by the Lawes of England: if once you paſſe thoſe bounds, and trench upon the prerogative of the Crowne, and liberties of the people, your blood be upon your owne heads.</hi> For that was the price of a premunire in thoſe daies; for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till 5<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Eliz.</hi> it was lawfull for any man to kill one that was attainted in a Premunire: as it was to kill a Wolfe or a wild Dog: for ſaith our Law, a man attainted in a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munire; did <hi>caput gerere lupinum:</hi> but now by that mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Stat. of 5. <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 1. it is unlawfull for any to kill a man attainted in a Premunire, and ſo I conclude the ſecond part of the diviſion.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:57493:16"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> I come now to the third, which is the maine and principall point of this Caſe, namely, to ſhew the ground and reaſons of Law, why the Clergy have in this particular caſe, in making Cannons, and forcing the execution of them upon the people by the cenſures of the Church, incurred a Premunire: which Grounds of Law are three.</p>
            <p>Firſt Ground is this, Clergie-men which only by Law have a ſpirituall Juriſdiction, if they ſhall exerciſe a Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction within the Kingdome, which only belongs to the Kings temporall Courts and not to their eccleſiaſticall Courts, they doe an act herein againſt the Kings Supremacy and Royall Prerogative, and ſo incurre a Premunire. The Bookes in our Law to prove this ground are many, which for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity ſake, I will only quote the authorities of Law, without putting the Caſes at large, becauſe I have much more to ſay: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>. N. Br.</hi> 152.5. <hi>Edw.</hi> 4. <hi>fob.</hi> 6.11<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. <hi>Bro. pram</hi> 12.44<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. fo. 36<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 15<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. <hi>per Fineux.</hi> 9. <hi>Edw.</hi> 4. <hi>D.</hi> &amp; St. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 24. &amp; <hi>cap.</hi> 32.</p>
            <p>The Reaſons of this ground are three.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſon </seg>1</label> By this meanes an act is done againſt Royall Majeſty, that is ſaith the Booke, 5. <hi>Edw.</hi> 4. <hi>fol.</hi> 6. againſt the Common Law, wherein is to be noted, that there is a mutuall dependance betweene the Kings Prerogative and the Common Law, that to violate the Common Law, is to doe an act againſt the Kings prerogative, and to violate the Prerogative, is to doe an act againſt the Common Law: with this agrees King <hi>James,</hi> in an excellent Parliament ſpeech of his, <hi>Anno</hi> 1609. Wherein he takes an occaſion to magnifie the Common Law, as moſt beneficiall to his Prerogative, and to deſpiſe it ſaith he, is to deſpiſe the Crowne.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Reaſon is given by <hi>D. St. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 32, that when debts and treſpaſſes, and ſuch other temporall matters are handled in the ſpirituall Courts, the King looſeth his fines and amerce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſuch other duties due to him upon originall writs of Debt, Treſpaſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Reaſon is given by the Stat. of 25. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.34. <hi>Ean.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. by which Stat. <hi>Magna Charta</hi> is appointed to be read in all Cathedrall Churches twice every yeare, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:57493:17"/>excommunications are then ſolemnly to be denounced againſt all infringers of the ſame, now there is no ſuch infringment of liberty, as to draw the ſubject into the Spirituall Courts by Cannons made by them, contrary to Law and the liberty of the Subject, graunted to them by that great Charter. But the Rule is, <hi>longum iter per praecepta, breve per exempla.</hi> I will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore give you ſome examples and preſidents, Three againſt Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and two againſt Convocations themſelves in the point of Praemuniries.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">preſi. </seg>1</label> The firſt is <hi>Hill.</hi> 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>Rot.</hi> 15. <hi>Cor. Rege Richard. Nix</hi> his Caſe, the blind Biſhop of <hi>Norwich,</hi> who for citing <hi>ex officio Richard Cockerall</hi> Major of <hi>Thetford</hi> into his Court, for taking a preſentment of a Jury in the Majors Court, who found that by an antient cuſtome and uſage, none ought to be ſued out of the Deanary of <hi>Thetford</hi> for any eccleſiaſticall matter, and that if any did ſue any Citations elſewhere, he was to pay a noble, For receiving this preſentment, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor was ſued in the Biſhops Court: for which <hi>Hales</hi> then the Kings Atturney did proſecute the Biſhop in a premunire, of which he was attainted, part of whoſe fine did goe to the glaſing of the windowes of the Kings Colledge Chappell in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Preſident is, <hi>Trin.</hi> 36. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>Rot.</hi> 9. <hi>Cor' Rege, Anthony Buckley</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Bangor,</hi> was proſecuted in a Premunire by <hi>Whorewood</hi> the Kings Atturney generall, for holding plea of right of Patronage, and of the ſale of Corne and graine ſold to <hi>Rice Ween, John ap Hugh</hi> and <hi>Tho. ap Hoell,</hi> and divers others, for 21<hi rend="sup">lb.</hi> upon ſeverall ſpecialties, which are matters only triable in the Kings Temporall Courts, did likewiſe incurre a Premunire, and was thereupon attainted, and his lands and goods forfeited.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Preſident was likewiſe in the Caſe of another Biſhop of <hi>Norwich,</hi> called <hi>William Bateman,</hi> who meerely for viſiting the Abbey of S. <hi>Edmundſbury,</hi> diſcharged antiently by divers Charters of Epiſcopall viſitations (the Abbot thereof being <hi>mitratus Abbas</hi>) was for this offence fined to the King in 30. talents of gold, which amounted to the ſumme of 3000<hi rend="sup">lb.</hi> and here by the way, being upon the preſident of a Biſhop of <hi>Norwich,</hi> I crave leave before I goe to other preſidents to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:57493:17"/>obſerve this one note, I doe finde that in all ages, the Biſhops of <hi>Norwich,</hi> above all other Biſhops in the Kingdome, were moſt active and pragmaticall, in advancing the eccleſiaſticall Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, and perſecuting the Miniſters of GOD: To give you one inſtance inſtead of many, it was a Biſhop of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich</hi> that was the firſt author of ſpilling the blood of the firſt Martyr we had here in England, named <hi>William Sawtree,</hi> that was burnt to death by the Writ <hi>de Heretico cumburendo,</hi> mentioned in the Regiſter, in <hi>Fitz. N. B. fo.</hi> 170. Where the very Name of <hi>William Sawtree</hi> is expreſſed in the Writ, who was Parſon of S. <hi>Margarets</hi> in <hi>Linne,</hi> in the Dioceſſe of <hi>Norwich,</hi> and was convicted before the Biſhop for the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of CHRIST, which was then counted Hereſie, and by him delivered over to <hi>Thomas Arundell</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> who cauſed him to be burnt to aſhes, and if the Biſhops of <hi>Norwich</hi> doe thinke this any praiſe to them, let them rejoyce in it: I ſhall only ſay this for the honour of that <hi>William Sawtree,</hi> and of <hi>Pembrook</hi>-Hall in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> above any Colledge either in <hi>Oxford</hi> or <hi>Cambridge,</hi> that <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrum primus,</hi> which was this <hi>William Sawtree, Martyrum doctiſſimus,</hi> which was Biſhop <hi>Ridley,</hi> and <hi>Martyrum pijſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> which was <hi>John Bradford,</hi> were all of <hi>Pembrook</hi> Hall.</p>
            <p>I come now to give preſidents, wherein the whole Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation were attainted in a Premunire, which are two,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is 7. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>Kell. Rep. fo.</hi> 181. The Abbot of <hi>Winſcombs</hi> caſe, which hath beene ſo often cited in this Houſe, but I ſhall only urge it to this one point, That the Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for meere citing <hi>ex officio,</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Standiſh</hi> for maintaining the Kings Prerogative and the Lawes of the land, that Prieſts ought to anſwer before temporall Judges, contrary to the tenent of the Clergy and the Abbots Sermon at <hi>Paules-Croſſe,</hi> The whole Convocation for this very act incurr'd a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munire by the reſolution of all the Judges of England aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled together by the King for their opinions in that Caſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond preſident is that of Cardinall <hi>Woolſey,</hi> which I firſt cited in Doctor <hi>Coſens</hi> his Caſe, and is full to this point,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:57493:18"/>it is <hi>Mich.</hi> 21. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>B. Roy.</hi> and the maine point of the Premunire was this, <hi>Quia ipſe intendebat antiquiſſimas Ang. leges penitus ſubvertere &amp; enervare, univerſum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> regnum Angl. legibus Civilibus, &amp; earundum legum Canonibus in perpetuum ſubjugare.</hi> This was found againſt him, and he was attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in a Premunire, though he had the Kings Commiſſion for what he did, and the King made meanes to the Pope to make him a Cardinall, and gave way that two Croſſes ſhould be carried before him, one as Cardinall, and the other as Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Yorke.</hi> Theſe <hi>Leges Civiles</hi> mentioned in that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, were the Legantine Conſtitutions exerciſed by the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall and all the Biſhops of England, in all their ſeverall Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, which though it had the countenance of the Kings Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to warrant, yet that was found no excuſe for ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt an act, for both Cardinall and all the Biſhops of the land, were adjudged to have incurr'd a Premunire, and therefore all the Biſhops did for their pardon of the ſaid Premunire, in their Convocation being then aſſembled and in time of Parliament, pay the King a huge maſſe of money, namely the Province of <hi>Canterbury</hi> paid the King 100000<hi rend="sup">lb</hi>. the Province of <hi>Yorke,</hi> 18840<hi rend="sup">lb</hi>. and the Cardinall himſelfe forfeited to the King, all his goods and Chattles, and all his lands and tenements, as <hi>Whitehall, Hampton Court, Christ Colledge</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This caſe doth juſtly agree with this Caſe before us, for here the Convocation have made Cannons, and added ſevere puniſhments to them, contrary to the Kings Prerogative, and the Lawes and Statutes of the Realme, which I made ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in my Argument concerning the Cannons, and therefore I will not ſpeake of them now, but will give you two inſtances which I did not mention then.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is in the firſt Cannon, by decreeing men to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed in the High Commiſſion, for teaching contrary to their explanations of Royall power and propertie of goods, being two things, of which the interpretation doth not belong to them, but to the Common Law, and to the Judges which are the expounders thereof. Beſides, they had no authority in the world to puniſh men in the High Commiſſion for ſuch things, for the laſt Letters Pattens of the High Commiſſion,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:57493:18"/>were <hi>Mich.</hi> 9. <hi>Car.</hi> in which are conteined all things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Commiſſioners were to meddle. And therefore it was impoſſible that theſe new Cannons, being made not a yeare agoe, ſhould be comprehended in thoſe Letters Pattents, of which the Framers thereof could not poſſibly take notice, unleſſe they had the Spirit of propheſie, which is not to be imagined, and therefore it was a bold attempt upon the Kings Prerogative, to order men to be puniſhed by vertue of his Comimſſion which gave them no ſuch authority.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond Inſtance is in the Cannons which they made for the payment of the Benevolence of the 6. Subſedies, which they ordered Clergy men to pay, upon the ſevereſt cenſures of the Church, as ſuſpenſion, deprivation, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with this clauſe added, <hi>omni appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latione ſemota,</hi> that is, without any manner of appeale to be allowed, which is a flat deniall of the Kings Subjects to have the benefit of Law, for in their owne Law appeales are to be allowed from the Ordinaries Court to the Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan, from the Metropolitan to the Pope, and ſuch au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in appeales as the Pope had, is now given to the King and his Judges <hi>Deligats</hi> by the Statutes of 24. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 12.25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 19. But in this caſe all appeales to the King are denied, and his Subjects muſt not only be excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated, but deprived of their free holds, and denied all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of appeale to helpe them, which is a high point of Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation upon the Crowne and the Lawes of the land, and an exerciſing of an Arbitrary power of their owne, above and againſt Law.</p>
            <p>The Second ground of Law,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Ground</hi>
               </note> why the Clergy in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation have incurr'd a Premunire, is this, If the King by his Commiſſion gives power to ſpirituall Judges to doe ſuch and ſuch acts, qualified by a proviſo to be done in ſuch and ſuch a manner, and with ſuch reſtrictions and limitations as are contained in that proviſo, and thoſe Judges will by colour of ſuch Commiſſion, doe acts contrary to ſuch proviſoes and limitations, they do hereby incurre a Premunire.</p>
            <p>As for example, the King by his Letters Pattents, appoints one to be a Biſhop, and limits the <hi>Deane</hi> and <hi>Chapter</hi> to Chuſe,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:57493:19"/>and the Arch-biſhop to conſecrate him within 12. dayes and they do contrary to this limitation, they do hereby incur a Premunire, as may appeare by the Stat. of 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>ca.</hi> 20.</p>
            <p>So by the Stat: of 1. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. before the Stat. of 1. Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> which repealed that Sta. of <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. all Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ops were to keepe their Courts by Commiſſion from the King, and not in their owne names, and the acts of the Court, to be under the Kings ſeale, and not under the Biſhops, and if they did the contrary they were to incurre fine and impriſonment in nature of a Premunire.</p>
            <p>To apply this to our caſe, the Kings Commiſſion for the Clergy to make Cannons in their pretended Synod, did beare date 12. May laſt paſte, being ſeven dayes after the diſſolving of the laſt Parliament, in which Commiſſion there was an expreſſe proviſo, that no Cannons ſhould be made,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Contrary to the Rubrick.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Contrary to the 39. Articles of Religion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Contrary to the Orders and Ceremonies already eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and yet as if they would do things purpoſely againſt the Kings Commiſſion, the Cannons that they made were contrary to all theſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, They were contrary to the Rubrick, of which, becauſe I will not be over-tedious, I will give but one inſtance, <hi>viz.</hi> the Rubrick before the Communion, confirmed by Act of Parliament; where it is expreſſely ſaid, that the Communion Table ſhall ſtand in the body of the Church or Chancell, and the Prieſt ſhall officiate at the North-ſide of the Table, by theſe Cannons, <hi>viz.</hi> the 7. Cannon, the Table is to be at the Eaſt end of the Chancell, to ſtand Altar-wiſe, and the ſides of the Table are to ſtand Eaſt and Weſt, and not North and South, and it is there called Altar and not Table, and men are injoyned to kneele at the Table, ſo removed, all contrary to the ſaid Rubrick; and though this may ſeem but a light matter, yet when I ſhall open to you the Reaſons of this upon the firſt Reformation, it will appeare to be a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of great weight and conſequence; for the people were in the time of <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. who began our Reformation of Religion,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:57493:19"/>addicted to groſſe Idolatry, by holding the opinion of tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, and by upholding that abominable Idoll of the Maſſe, in the Adoration of the Hoaſt, and the way then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed to reduce them from Idolatry, was by this meanes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, King <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. did by his injunction cauſe all Altars to be pulled downe, and moveable Tables of wood to be in their Rooms.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, he did appoint that the Sacrament ſhould be no more called the Sacrament of the Altar, but the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the body and blood of CHRIST, and that the Table on which the bread and wine did ſtand, ſhould be called a Table and not an Altar, as may appeare by the Stat. of 1. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. <hi>Cap.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, He did appoint the Table to ſtand in the body of the Church by his Common-prayer Booke, 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. to the end that the people might forget their adoration at the place where it ſtood before.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly and laſtly, To take away all manner of Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he cauſed a declaration to be made of the ſence and meaning of the Church of England, for the geſture of knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at the Communion, which is ſet downe at large in the Common-prayer Book, which was ſet out, 5. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. which becauſe it hath given ſatisfaction to the Conſciences of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundreds, and is now left out of our Common-prayer Books, I will take the boldneſſe to reade it to you word for word, as I find it in that Rubrick, becauſe it is of ſingular uſe.</p>
            <p>Although no order can be ſo perfectly deviſed, but it may be of ſome, either for their ignorance and infirmity, or els of malice and obſtinacy miſconſtrued, depraved and interpreted in a wrong part, and yet becauſe brotherly charity willeth, that ſo much as conveniently may be, offences ſhould be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, therfore we willing to doe the ſame: Whereas it is ordained in the Book of Common-prayer, in the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lords Supper, that the Communicants kneeling ſhould receive the holy Communion; which thing being well meant for a ſignification of the humble and gratefull ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:57493:20"/>of the benefits of CHRIST given unto the worthy receiver, and to avoid the prophanation and diſorder, which about the holy Communion might els enſue, leaſt the ſame kneeling might be thought or taken otherwiſe, we do declare that it is not meant therby, that any adoration is done, or ought to be done, either unto the Sacramentall Bread and Wine, there bodily received, or unto any reall and eſſentiall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence there being of CHRISTS naturall fleſh and bloud; for as concerning the Sacramentall Bread and Wine, they remaine ſtill in their very naturall ſubſtances, and therfore may not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dored, for that were Idolatry to be abhorr'd of all faithfull Chriſtians, and as concerning the naturall Body and Blood of our Saviour CHRIST, they are in Heaven and not here, for it is againſt the Truth of CHRISTS true naturall Body to be in moe places then in one at one time.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, the 7. Cannon (to name no more) is againſt the 39. Articles which are confirmed by the Parliament 13. <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 12. which I prove in this manner, the 35. Article doth maintaine the Books of Homilies to containe good and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome doctrine; now the ſeventh Cannon approoving of the bowing in Churches and at Communion Tables is expreſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt 3 Homilies of the Church of Eng. <hi>viz.</hi> 1. <hi>The Homily of the right uſe of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Homily of repairing the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. And the ſecond and third <hi>Homilies of the perill of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry;</hi> In all which Homilies you ſhall finde theſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Images and I dols are all one.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That Altars and Images are one.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That Idolatry is to Images in Temples an inſeperable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That in time of Common-prayer, private devotion is not to be uſed.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That the true ornaments of the Church, conſiſt in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, prayer, due adminiſtration of the Sacraments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and not by any outward Ceremonies, or coſtly and glorious decking of the Houſe of GOD with gold, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioning men thereby to commit moſt horrible Idolatry.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:57493:20"/> 6. That the Church is called holy, not of it ſelfe, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe GODS people reſorting thereunto are holy, with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers more paſſages in thoſe Homilies to that purpoſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I inferre, that in aſmuch as the 7. Cannon and other Cannons are oppoſite to theſe paſſages, they have made Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons againſt the 35. Article of Religion, and ſo have done con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Proviſo in the Commiſſion.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, By the 7. Cannon, and other their new Cannons they have done againſt their Commiſſion, in that they are againſt the Ceremonies of the Church of England now eſtabliſhed ſince the Reformation. For by the 82. Cannon in the Cannons 1. <hi>Jaco.</hi> the Table is to ſtand in the body of the Church or Chancell, to the end that the greater number may commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate at the Table, and the Miniſter may be the better heard and ſeene: But by the ſetting of the Table at the Eaſt end of the Chancell, the greater number cannot communicate, and the Miniſter in divers places cannot be heard or ſcarcely ſeene, whereupon I conclude this ſecond ground of Law, that becauſe the Clergy have done ſo directly againſt their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from the King, they have thereby incurred a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munire.</p>
            <p>The third Ground of Law wherewith I will conclude the third part of my diviſion is this.
<note place="margin">3 <hi>Ground</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>The Common Law of England, which as King <hi>James</hi> ſaith, is in its own principalls the juſteſt Law in the world, ſhould not in our caſe be juſt (the Clergy themſelvs being Judges) if they of the Convocation ſhould not incurre a Premu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire.</p>
            <p>As it is a rule in Art, <hi>Contrariorum contrariaeſt ratio,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Subject, ſo there is another rule in Art, <hi>Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riorum eadem eſt ratio,</hi> in reſpect of the Analogy and propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for doe but obſerve what they doe againſt us in the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc. Conſtitut. cap. de ſententia excom.</hi> (which is good Law with the Clergy) you ſhall find theſe words, <hi>Excommunican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur omnes illi qui literas impetrant à quacun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> curia laicali ad im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediend. proceſſum Eccleſiaſt. Judicum in cauſis qua per ſacros Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nones ad forum Eccleſ. pertinent.</hi> Nay ſo high they go in their advancement of their Eccleſiaſticall Juriſdiction, that in the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:57493:21"/>ſaid Conſtitutions, <hi>capite de panis,</hi> it doth appeare, that if the King do by writ or other command call a Biſhop to anſwer in his temporall Court, and the Sheriff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> execute thoſe writs by diſtreſſe or attachment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The King indeed is in point of good manners admoniſhed by them, 1, 2, 3. according to forme, but if he will not then deſiſt, but <hi>in ſua duritia perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verare</hi> (for ſuch rebellious words they have) the King, his Officers and Miniſters, his Mannors, Caſtles, Cities, Burrows, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are hereby expoſed to excommunication and interdiction, which how terrible it was to the Kingdome of England may appeare in the example of King <hi>Iohn,</hi> who was excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and his Kingdome interdicted by his owne Biſhops, all the Church doores in the Realme locked up, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, chriſtnings and burialls denied to all his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>To apply this to our caſe, If the King and his people are thus uſed by the Clergy for the maintenance of their own Lawes as to exclude them from Heaven, from the Church, and from Salvation, for ſo are excommunicated perſons, <hi>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam Ethnici &amp; publicani,</hi> it is then moſt juſt for the King, to exclude the Clergy from the protection and benefit of his Laws, when they ſo incroach and intrench upon them, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that ancient rule of Law, <hi>Fruſtra legis auxilium invocat qui in legem committit:</hi> And ſo M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. SPEAKER, I have done with the third and maine part of my Diuiſion and come to the fourth and laſt, which is the anſwer of Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons mooved principally by three learned <hi>Civilians</hi> (for ſo I muſt account them) Doct. <hi>Cowell</hi> in his Interpreter <hi>verbo praemunire,</hi> a booke ſuppreſſed by Parliament, and King <hi>Iames</hi> Proclamation, but of late reprinted, Doct. <hi>Coſins</hi> Deane of the Arches in the time of Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in his Apology for Eccleſiaſticall proceedings, and Doct. <hi>Ridley</hi> vicar gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall in the time of King <hi>Iames,</hi> in his view of the Civill and Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non Laws.</p>
            <p>The Objections are ſix.
<note place="margin">Fourth part.</note> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ob. </seg>1</label> The firſt Objection is this; the Law of England, ſayth <hi>Civilians,</hi> doth not impute Premunire to any ſpirituall Judge, dealing in a temporall matter, but onely prohibition.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:57493:21"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">anſw. </seg>
               </label> To this I anſwer, that it is a fallacy, <hi>ex ignoratione Elen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chi,</hi> as Logitians call it, that is a meere miſtake of the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, for the difference in our Law, is this; where the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Court hath juriſdiction and where not, as for example, The ſpirituall Court hath juriſdiction of Tithes, and yet if it hold plea, <hi>de groſſis arboribus,</hi> that is of Timber-trees above 20. yeares growth, contrary to the Stat. of <hi>ſilva caedua,</hi> 45. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. there a prohibition onely doth lye, becauſe the Court hath juriſdiction of Tythes; but when the ſpirituall Court hath no juriſdiction at all, as in debt, treſpaſſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> there a premunire doth lye. So is D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. and <hi>St.</hi> which I quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before, and 24. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>B.</hi> Prem. 16. and divers other authorities in Law.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ob. </seg>2</label> It is ſaid by the Civilians, that <hi>Curia Romana aut alibi,</hi> mentioned in the Statutes of Premunires, which I cited be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, muſt not be meant of any Courts here in England, but of the Popes Courts, which he kept ſometimes at <hi>Rome,</hi> ſometimes at <hi>Avignion</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and ſometimes at <hi>Bonony</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> and therefore muſt be ment of thoſe Courts, which the Pope kept beyond Sea, and not at <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">anſw. </seg>
               </label> It is a vain Objection, for <hi>alibi</hi> doth not referre to the place, but to the Court; for wherſoever the Pope is, let him be at <hi>Rome,</hi> at <hi>Avignion,</hi> at <hi>Bonony</hi> or in <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. There is <hi>Curia Romana</hi> wherſoever he is, and therfore <hi>alibi</hi> muſt needs be ment of ſome other Eccleſiaſticall Court then the Popes Court, and ſo is it expounded in old <hi>N. B. fol.</hi> 152. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5. <hi>Edw.</hi> 4. <hi>fol.</hi> 6. and divers other books of Law; and therefore in ſome of the Records which I cited before, the word <hi>alibi</hi> is thus interpreted, <hi>In Curia Romana aut aliqua a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia Curia Chriſtianitatis,</hi> and that is certainly the meaning of the word <hi>alibi,</hi> as may appeare by the pleading in the old booke of Entries 430. <hi>Praedict. I. R. machinans Dominum Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem nunc coronam &amp; dignitatem ſuam exhaeredare, &amp; cognitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem quae ad curiam Domini Regis pertinet ad aliud examen trahere:</hi> for that indeed was the only miſchief to draw the Kings Subjects for temporall matters to a tryall in the Eccleſiaſticall Courts of which they had no cognizance.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ob. </seg>3</label> The ſpirituall Courts ſhould in this caſe, ſay they, bee
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:57493:22"/>worſe then an inferiour Court Baron, for there no Premunire doth lye, if the Lord doth hold plea of actions above 40<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">anſw. </seg>
               </label> This is another fallacy, which Logicians call <hi>petitio principij,</hi> a begging of the queſtion, for old <hi>Nat. B. fo.</hi> 153. is to the contrary.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Beſides, if the Law were otherwiſe, yet a Court Baron is a Court of Common Law and antient, and the ſpirituall Court is a Court of the Cannon Law and not antient.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ob. </seg>4</label> The Eccleſiaſticall Courts ſay they are now become the Kings Courts, by the Statute of 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Eliz. Cap.</hi> 1. as other Courts in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Hall, and therfore the King can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have a Premunire againſt himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">anſw. </seg>
               </label> I deny this, For they are the Kings Courts now, no more then they were before, for the Stat. of 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Eliz.</hi> did not give the King any new power, but only reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the old which hee had before: and this anſwer did Chancellour <hi>Audley</hi> give to <hi>Stephen Gardiner</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Winchester,</hi> who made this objection; telling him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, that the Premunire was a Rod that the Common Law had to keepe the Biſhops in awe, and to reduce them to good order, otherwiſe men would have no quiet for them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> They cannot now make this Objection, becauſe they keepe their eccleſiaſticall Courts in their owne names, and not in the Kings, having procured a Proclamation, 1637. declaring the opinions of the Judges; that the Stat. of 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. is repealed, and of no force at this day, and that Biſhops may keepe Courts in their owne names.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ob. </seg>5</label> It is objected by the Clergy, that theſe new Cannons were made by authority of the King, by his Commiſſion dated 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Maij</hi> laſt, and therefore they had a warrant for what they did.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">anſw. </seg>
               </label> This is no excuſe, for if the Cannons which they made be contrary to the proviſo in their Commiſſion, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Law, which I have proved before, this is ſo farre
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:57493:22"/>from excuſing, that it aggravates their offence, for hereby the King, which by Law can doe no wrong to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, is by this Commiſſion made by them an inſtrument of injury to his people. Divines ſay, <hi>ſimulata ſanctitas duplex iniquitas,</hi> becauſe to the outward breach of the Law, there is added an inward hypocriſie of the heart, which doubles the ſinne. So in acts of Injuſtice countenanced by Law, there is added to the Injuſtice a deceipt to the King, which dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles the offence. Many examples may be given in this kind, I will only name three,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Cardinall <hi>Woolſey</hi> had a Commiſſion from the King, for keeping his Legantine Courts, but yet this Commiſſion was no excuſe to preſerve him from an attainder in a Premunire, as I ſaid before.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Stephen Gardiner</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> in his letter to the Lord Protector, mentioned in the firſt Edition of the Acts and Monuments of the Church, (but left out in the latter) doth cite the Lord <hi>Tiptofts</hi> caſe, who had a Commiſſion from the King, to execute divers things, which being found in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution to be againſt Law, he loſt both his head and his Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion at <hi>Tower Hill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The third and laſt example is S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Anthony Mildmayes</hi> caſe, 14<hi rend="sup">o</hi>, <hi>Jacob.</hi> in the <hi>Kings Bench,</hi> who was a Commiſſioner of the <hi>Sewers,</hi> which Commiſſion is grounded upon the Statute of 23<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. who by vertue of his Commiſſion, did cauſe one to be diſtrained for a fine impoſed upon him by vertue of the Commiſſion of <hi>Sewers,</hi> who brought an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of treſpaſſe againſt the partie that diſtrained him, and had judgement to recover, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Anthony Mildmay</hi> by an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from the <hi>Sewers,</hi> cauſed him to be impriſoned till hee had releaſed the judgement, for which offence, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Anthony Mildmay</hi> was ſued in a Premunire in the <hi>Kings Bench,</hi> to which he pleaded, and was faine to procure a pardon from the King for his diſcharge.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ob. </seg>6</label> The laſt and greateſt Objection is this, The Biſhop of <hi>Exceter,</hi> and divers Divines more, hold that the Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of Biſhops is <hi>jure divino,</hi> whereupon it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owes, that neither prohibition nor Premunire, can
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:57493:23"/>reſtraine that Juriſdiction which derives from the Law of GOD.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">anſw. </seg>
               </label> This indeed is true, if their Juriſdiction were of that nature, but I have proved before by divers Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that their Juriſdiction is acknowledged by the Law of England, onely to be <hi>jure humano,</hi> ſo are the Statutes of 35. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. called the Statute of <hi>Carliel,</hi> 25<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3.25<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.26. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.37. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Eliz.</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Co.</hi> 5. <hi>Rep. Cawdries</hi> caſe.</p>
            <p>The Common Law doth agree with theſe Statutes, for the Canoniſts as heretofore I have told you, doe obſerve a double power to be in a Biſhop,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Poteſtas ordinis,</hi> common with other Miniſters, as to Preach, Baptize, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Poteſtas Juriſdictionis,</hi> as to admit, inſtitute, deprive, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The former they ſay, is <hi>de jure divino,</hi> the latter is, <hi>de jure Canonnico</hi> or <hi>poſitivo,</hi> which is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Statutes I cited before, but what doe I ſpeake of the Common Law, for the very Church of England ſeemes to be of this opinion, for in our Booke of Common prayer, no more is allowed to Biſhops, in point of divine right, then what is common with Paſtors, Miniſters and Curats, for there are but three prayers for Biſhops in all the Booke of Common prayer, and they all runne to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is in the Lettany, in theſe words, <hi>that it may pleaſe thee to illuminate all Biſhops, Paſtors and Ministers of the Church, with true knowledge and underſtanding of thy word, that both by their preaching and living, they may ſet it forth and ſhew it accordingly,</hi> wherein nothing is mentioned but their knowledge of GODS word, their good life and doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The next prayer for them, is after the prayer for the King and his Children in theſe wordes, <hi>That God would ſend downe upon all our Biſhops and Curats, and all Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions committed to their charge, the helpefull spirit of his grace, that they may truly pleaſe him,</hi> &amp;c. where the taking care of the cure of ſoules in Congregations committed
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:57493:23"/>to them, is the maine thing which we pray for them on their behalfe.</p>
            <p>The laſt is in the prayer for the militant Church, in theſe words, <hi>Give grace (O heavenly Father,) to all Biſhops, Paſtors and Curats, that they may both by their life and doctrine, ſet forth thy true and lively word, and rightly and duely adminiſter thy holy Sacraments,</hi> where there is not ſo much as a word men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned of their Juriſdiction, but of their true preaching, good living, and due adminiſtration of the Sacraments.</p>
            <p>And ſo M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Speaker, doe I conclude my whole Argument, touching the penalty incurred by the Clergy for their illegall Cannons, made in their Synod at <hi>Paules,</hi> concerning which, I will end all in theſe two Verſes, which may be better applied to this Synod, then the <hi>Arminians</hi> applied them to the Synod at <hi>Dort,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Paulinae Synodus nodus Chorus, integer aeger,</l>
                  <l>Conventus ventus, Seſſio ſtramen, Amen.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
